=== PAGE 6 ===
The diffusion models pθ(·|s) produce discrete variables x as the final pre-
dictions by applying Bernoulli sampling (Eq. 6) for discrete diffusion or quantization for continuous
diffusion. However, this process discards the comparative information that reflects the confidence
of the predicted variables, which is crucial for resolving conflicts in the decoding process. To
preserve this information, we adapt the diffusion models to generate heatmaps [53, 92] by making
the following appropriate modifications: 1) For discrete diffusion, the final score of pθ(x0 = 1|s)
is preserved as the heatmap scores; 2) For continuous diffusion, we remove the final quantization
and use 0.5(ˆx0 + 1) as the heatmap scores. Note that different from previous heatmap approaches
[53, 92] that produce a single conditionally independent distribution for all variables, DIFUSCO can
produce diverse multimodal output distribution by using different random seeds.
Let {Aij} be the heatmap scores generated by DIFUSCO denoting the confidence
of each edge. We evaluate two approaches as the decoding method following previous work [32, 92]:
1) Greedy decoding [32], where all the edges are ranked by (Aij + Aji)/∥ci −cj∥, and are inserted
into the partial solution if there are no conflicts. 2-opt heuristics [71] are optionally applied. 2)
Monte Carlo Tree Search (MCTS) [27], where k-opt transformation actions are sampled guided by
the heatmap scores to improve the current solutions. Due to the space limit, a detailed description of
two decoding strategies can be found in the appendix.
Let {ai} be the heatmap scores generated by DIFUSCO denoting the confidence
of each node. A greedy decoding strategy is used for the MIS problem, where the nodes are ranked
by ai and inserted into the partial solution if there are no conflicts. Recent research [8] pointed out
that the graph reduction and 2-opt search [2] can find near-optimal solutions even starting from a
randomly generated solution, so we do not use any post-processing for the greedy-decoded solutions.
A common practice for probabilistic CO solvers [64] is to sample multiple
solutions and report the best one. For DIFUSCO, we follow this practice by sampling multiple
heatmaps from pθ(x0|s) with different random seeds and then applying the greedy decoding algorithm
described above to each heatmap.
We use 2-D Euclidean TSP instances to test our models. We generate these instances by randomly
sampling nodes from a uniform distribution over the unit square. We use TSP-50 (with 50 nodes)
as the main benchmark to compare different model configurations. We also evaluate our method
on larger TSP instances with 100, 500, 1000, and 10000 nodes to demonstrate its scalability and
performance against other state-of-the-art methods.
We generate and label the training instances using the Concorde exact solver [3] for
TSP-50/100 and the LKH-3 heuristic solver [39] for TSP-500/1000/10000. We use the same test
instances as [54, 64] for TSP-50/100 and [27] for TSP-500/1000/10000.
We use sparse graphs for large-scale TSP problems to reduce the computa-
tional complexity. We sparsify the graphs by limiting each node to have only k edges to its nearest
neighbors based on the Euclidean distances. We set k to 50 for TSP-500 and 100 for TSP-1000/10000.
This way, we avoid the quadratic growth of edges in dense graphs as the number of nodes increases.
T = 1000 denoising steps are used for the training of DIFUSCO on all datasets.
Following Ho et al. [40], Graikos et al. [32], we use a simple linear noise schedule for {βt}T
β1 = 10−4 and βT = 0.02. We follow Graikos et al. [32] and use the Greedy decoding + 2-opt
scheme (Sec. 3.5) as the default decoding scheme for experiments.
In order to compare the performance of different models, we present three
metrics: average tour length (Length), average relative performance gap (Gap), and total run time
(Time). The detailed description can be found in the appendix.

=== PAGE 7 ===
ous (Gaussian noise) and discrete
(Bernoulli noise) diffusion models
with different inference diffusion steps
and inference schedule (linear v.s.
Table 1: Comparing results on TSP-50 and TSP-100. ∗denotes the
baseline for computing the performance gap.
† indicates that the
diffusion model samples a single solution as its greedy decoding
scheme. Please refer to Sec. 4 for details.
Figure 2: The performance Gap (%) are shown for continuous diffusion (a) and discrete diffusion (b) models on
TSP-50 with different diffusion steps and number of samples. Their corresponding per-instance run-time (sec)
are shown in (c), where the decomposed analysis (neural network + greedy decoding + 2-opt) can be found in
Discrete Diffusion v.s. Continuous Diffusion
We first investigate the suitability of two diffusion
approaches for combinatorial optimization, namely continuous diffusion with Gaussian noise and
discrete diffusion with Bernoulli noise (Sec. 3.2). Additionally, we explore the effectiveness of
different denoising schedules, such as linear and cosine schedules (Sec. 3.3), on CO problems.
To efficiently evaluate these model choices, we utilize the TSP-50 benchmark.
Note that although all the diffusion models are trained with a T = 1000 noise schedule, the inference
schedule can be shorter than T, as described in Sec. 3.3. Specifically, we are interested in diffusion
models with 1, 2, 5, 10, 20, 50, 100, and 200 diffusion steps.
Fig. 1 demonstrates the performance of two types of diffusion models with two types of inference
schedules and various diffusion steps. We can see that discrete diffusion consistently outperforms
the continuous diffusion models by a large margin when there are more than 5 diffusion steps2.
Besides, the cosine schedule is superior to linear on discrete diffusion and performs similarly on
continuous diffusion. Therefore, we use cosine for the rest of the paper.
More Diffusion Iterations v.s. More Sampling
By utilizing effective denoising schedules, diffu-
sion models are able to adaptively infer based on the available computation budget by predetermining
the total number of diffusion steps. This is similar to changing the number of samples in previous
probabilistic neural NPC solvers [64]. Therefore, we investigate the trade-off between the number of
diffusion iterations and the number of samples for diffusion-based NPC solvers.
2We also observe similar patterns on TSP-100, where the results are reported in the appendix.

=== PAGE 8 ===
Table 2: Results on large-scale TSP problems. RL, SL, AS, G, S, BS, and MCTS denotes Reinforcement
Learning, Supervised Learning, Active Search, Greedy decoding, Sampling decoding, Beam-search, and Monte
Carlo Tree Search, respectively. * indicates the baseline for computing the performance gap. Results of baselines
are taken from Fu et al. [27] and Qiu et al. [92], so the runtime may not be directly comparable. See Section 4
and appendix for detailed descriptions.
LKH-3 (LESS TRAILS) HEURISTICS
Fig. 2 shows the results of continuous diffusion and discrete diffusion with various diffusion steps and
number of parallel sampling, as well as their corresponding total run-time. The cosine denoising
schedule is used for fast inference. Again, we find that discrete diffusion outperforms continuous
diffusion across various settings. Besides, we find performing more diffusion iterations is generally
more effective than sampling more solutions, even when the former uses less computation. For exam-
ple, 20 (diffusion steps)×4 (samples) performs competitive to 1 (diffusion steps)×1024 (samples),
while the runtime of the former is 18.5× less than the latter.
In general, we find that 50 (diffusion steps) × 1 (samples) policy and 10 (diffusion steps) ×
16 (samples) policy make a good balance between exploration and exploitation for discrete DI-
FUSCO models and use them as the Greedy and Sampling strategies for the rest of the experiments.
Comparison to SOTA Methods
We compare discrete DIFUSCO to other state-of-the-art neural
NPC solvers on TSP problems across various scales. Due to the space limit, the description of other
baseline models can be found in the appendix.
Tab. 1 compare discrete DIFUSCO with other models on TSP-50 and TSP-100, where DIFUSCO
achieves the state-of-the-art performance in both greedy and sampling settings for probabilistic
Tab. 2 compare discrete DIFUSCO with other models on the larger-scale TSP-500, TSP-1000, and
TSP-10000 problems. Most previous probabilistic solvers (except DIMES [92]) becomes untrainable
on TSP problems of these scales, so the results of these models are reported with TSP-100 trained
models. The results are reported with greedy, sampling, and MCTS decoding strategies, respectively.
For fair comparisons [27, 92], MCTS decoding for TSP is always evaluated with only one sampled
heatmap. From the table, we can see that DIFUSCO strongly outperforms the previous neural solvers
on all three settings. In particular, with MCTS-based decoding, DIFUSCO significantly improving
the performance gap between ground-truth and neural solvers from 1.76% to 0.46% on TSP-500,
from 2.46% to 1.17% on TSP-1000, and from 3.19% to 2.58% on TSP-10000.

=== PAGE 9 ===
Figure 3: Generalization tests of DIFUSCO
trained and evaluated on TSP problems
across various scales. The performance Gap
(%) with greedy decoding and 2-opt is re-
Table 3: Results on MIS problems. ∗indicates the baseline for
computing the optimality gap. RL, SL, G, S, and TS denote Re-
inforcement Learning, Supervised Learning, Greedy decoding,
Sampling decoding, and Tree Search, respectively. Please refer
to Sec. 5 and appendix for details.
Finally, we study the generalization ability of discrete DIFUSCO trained
on a set of TSP problems of a specific problem scale and evaluated on other problem scales. From
Fig. 3, we can see that DIFUSCO has a strong generalization ability. In particular, the model trained
with TSP-50 perform well on even TSP-1000 and TSP0-10000. This pattern is different from the bad
generalization ability of RL-trained or SL-trained non-autoregressive methods as reported in previous
For Maximal Independent Set (MIS), we experiment on two types of graphs that recent work
[70, 1, 8, 92] shows struggles against, i.e., SATLIB [46] and Erd˝os-Rényi (ER) graphs [26]. The
former is a set of graphs reduced from SAT instances in CNF, while the latter are random graphs.
We use ER-[700-800] for evaluation, where ER-[n-N] indicates the graph contains n to N nodes.
Following Qiu et al. [92], the pairwise connection probability p is set to 0.15.
The training instances of labeled by the KaMIS3 heuristic solver. The split of test instances
on SAT datasets and the random-generated ER test graphs are taken from Qiu et al. [92].
The training schedule is the same as the TSP solver (Sec. 4.1). For SATLIB, we use
discrete diffusion with 50 (diffusion steps)×1 (samples) policy and 50 (diffusion steps)×4 (samples)
policy as the Greedy and Sampling strategies, respectively. For ER graphs, we use continuous
diffusion with 50 (diffusion steps) × 1 (samples) policy and 20 (diffusion steps) × 8 (samples)
policy as the Greedy and Sampling strategies, respectively.
We report the average size of the independent set (Size), average optimality
gap (Gap), and latency time (Time). The detailed description can be found in the appendix. Notice
that we disable graph reduction and 2-opt local search in all models for a fair comparison since it is
pointed out by [8] that all models would perform similarly with local search post-processing.
Tab. 3 compare discrete DIFUSCO with other baselines on SATLIB and
ER-[700-800] benchmarks. We can see that DIFUSCO strongly outperforms previous state-of-the-art
methods on SATLIB benchmark, reducing the gap between ground-truth and neural solvers from
0.63% to 0.21%. However, we also found that DIFUSCO (especially with discrete diffusion in our
preliminary experiments) does not perform well on the ER-[700-800] data. We hypothesize that this
is because the previous methods usually use the node-based graph neural networks such as GCN
[62] or GraphSage [36] as the backbone network, while we use an edge-based Anisotropic GNN
(Sec. 3.4), whose inductive bias may be not suitable for ER graphs.

