=== PAGE 1 ===
DualOpt: A Dual Divide-and-Optimize Algorithm for the Large-scale Traveling
Shipei Zhou1*, Yuandong Ding1*, Chi Zhang1, Zhiguang Cao2, Yan Jin1†
1School of Computer Science, Huazhong University of Science and Technology, China
2School of Computing and Information Systems, Singapore Management University, Singapore
This paper proposes a dual divide-and-optimize algorithm
(DualOpt) for solving the large-scale traveling salesman
problem (TSP). DualOpt combines two complementary
strategies to improve both solution quality and computa-
tional efficiency. The first strategy is a grid-based divide-and-
conquer procedure that partitions the TSP into smaller sub-
problems, solving them in parallel and iteratively refining the
solution by merging nodes and partial routes. The process
continues until only one grid remains, yielding a high-quality
initial solution. The second strategy involves a path-based
divide-and-optimize procedure that further optimizes the so-
lution by dividing it into sub-paths, optimizing each using a
neural solver, and merging them back to progressively im-
prove the overall solution. Extensive experiments conducted
on two groups of TSP benchmark instances, including ran-
domly generated instances with up to 100,000 nodes and real-
world datasets from TSPLIB, demonstrate the effectiveness
of DualOpt. The proposed DualOpt achieves highly compet-
itive results compared to 10 state-of-the-art algorithms in the
literature. In particular, DualOpt achieves an improvement
gap up to 1.40% for the largest instance TSP100K with a
remarkable 104x speed-up over the leading heuristic solver
LKH3. Additionally, DualOpt demonstrates strong general-
ization on TSPLIB benchmarks, confirming its capability to
tackle diverse real-world TSP applications.
The Traveling Salesman Problem (TSP) is an NP-hard com-
binatorial optimization problem, which has numerous real-
world applications (Madani, Batta, and Karwan 2021; Ha-
cizade and Kaya 2018; Matai, Singh, and Mittal 2010).
Let G = (V, E) represent an undirected graph, where
| 1 ≤i ≤N} is the set of nodes and
E = {eij | 1 ≤i, j ≤N} is the set of edges, with
N being the total number of nodes. For each edge eij, the
travel cost cost(i, j) is defined as the Euclidean distance be-
tween the nodes vi and vj. A special node vd ∈V serves
as the depot, from which the salesman starts and ends the
trip. A feasible solution of TSP is defined as a Hamilto-
nian cycle that starts from the depot, visits each node ex-
actly once, and ends at the depot. The objective is to mini-
mize the total travel cost of the solution route τ, denoted as
*These authors contributed equally.
†Yan Jin is the corresponding author: jinyan@mail.hust.edu.cn
cost(τi, τi+1) + cost(τN, τ1), where τi repre-
sents the i −th node in the route.
Due to its theoretical and practical interest, various tra-
ditional exact/heuristic and machine learning-based algo-
rithms have been proposed in the literature. While exact al-
gorithms are generally computationally infeasible for large-
scale instances, heuristics can provide near-optimal solu-
tions for TSP with millions of cities, though they cannot
guarantee optimality. They often involve time-consuming
iterative searches, making them less suitable for time-
sensitive tasks. Machine learning based algorithms, on the
other hand, offer high computational efficiency and can
achieve solution quality comparable to traditional methods
for small-scale TSP instances. However, applying them to
large-scale TSP, especially those with over 1,000 cities,
remains a challenge. One approach is to leverage pre-
trained models from small-scale instances for larger ones,
but this often results in poor performance due to distribu-
tion shift (Joshi et al. 2022). Training models specifically
for large-scale TSP is also impractical due to computational
A basic approach to deal with the large-scale routing
problem is to apply the general principle of “divide-and-
conquer” (Fu, Qiu, and Zha 2021; Pan et al. 2023; Hou et al.
2023; Chen et al. 2023; Ye et al. 2024b; ?; Xia et al. 2024).
It involves decomposing TSP into a subset of small sub-
problems, which can be efficiently solved using traditional
or machine learning algorithms to attain sub-solutions. The
final solution is then obtained by combining these sub-
solutions. This approach can significantly reduce the com-
putational complexity of the large-scale TSP, and yield high-
quality solutions in a relatively short time.
In this work, we introduce a novel dual divide-and-
optimize algorithm DualOpt based on the divide-and-
conquer framework. The first divide-and-optimize proce-
dure partitions the nodes into M × M equal-sized grids
based on their coordinates. The nodes within each grid are
initially solved using the well-known LKH3 solver (Hels-
gaun 2017). Next, an edge-breaking strategy is proposed to
decompose the route into partial routes and nodes, signif-
icantly reducing the number of nodes. Subsequently, every
four adjacent grids are merged into one larger grid. This pro-
arXiv:2501.08565v1  [cs.AI]  15 Jan 2025

=== PAGE 2 ===
cess is repeated until all nodes are contained within a sin-
gle grid, at which point the LKH3 solver is applied to ob-
tain a complete route based on the partial routes and nodes.
The second divide-and-optimize procedure further refines
the obtained route by partitioning it into non-overlapping
subpaths. These subpaths are then optimized in parallel us-
ing a neural solver (Kim, Park et al. 2021; Pan et al. 2023; Ye
et al. 2024b), ultimately leading to an optimized route. The
main contributions of this work are summarized as follows:
• We propose the DualOpt algorithm, which combines two
complementary divide-and-conquer frameworks to ad-
dress the large-scale TSP. The first framework employs
grid-based partitioning, while the second applies path-
based optimization, significantly improving both solution
quality and computational efficiency of large-scale TSP.
• We introduce a novel edge-breaking strategy that de-
composes routes into partial routes and nodes. By rep-
resenting these partial routes solely by their start and end
nodes, this strategy considerably reduces the number of
nodes, thereby decreasing computational complexity and
• We conduct extensive experiments on both randomly
generated and real-world large-scale TSP instances. To
the best of our knowledge, DualOpt achieves state-of-
the-art performance compared to other machine learning-
based approaches, particularly excelling in large-scale in-
stances with up to 100,000 nodes.
Here we present representative traditional and machine
learning-based algorithms to solve TSP, and then focus on
the divide-and-conquer algorithms that are more effective
for solving large-scale TSP over 1000 nodes.
Traditional algorithms can be
roughly classified into two categories: exact and heuristic al-
gorithms (Gutin and Punnen 2006; Accorsi and Vigo 2021).
Concorde (Applegate et al. 2009) is one of the best exact
solvers, which models TSP as a mixed-integer programming
problem and solves it using a branch-and-cut (Toth and Vigo
2002). Exact algorithms can theoretically guarantee optimal
solutions for instances of limited size, but are impractical
for solving large instances due to their inherent exponential
complexity. LKH3 (Helsgaun 2017) is one of the state-of-
the-art heuristics that uses the k-opt operators to find neigh-
boring solutions, which is guided by a α-nearness measure
based on the minimum spanning tree. The heuristics are the
most widely used algorithms in practice, yet they are still
time consuming to obtain high-quality solutions when solv-
ing problems with tens of thousands of nodes.
machine learning-based algorithms have attracted more in-
terest in solving the TSP. Depending on how solutions are
constructed, they can be broadly categorized into end-to-end
approaches and search-based approaches.
End-to-end approaches generate solutions from scratch.
The Attention Model (Kool, van Hoof, and Welling 2019)
utilizes the Transformer architecture (Vaswani et al. 2017)
and is trained with REINFORCE (Wiering and Van Otterlo
2012) using a greedy rollout baseline. POMO (Kwon et al.
2020) improves on this by selecting multiple nodes as start-
ing points, using symmetries in solution representation, and
employing a shared baseline to enhance REINFORCE train-
ing. DIFUSCO (Sun and Yang 2024) uses graph-based de-
noising diffusion models to generate solutions, which are
further optimized by local search with k-opt operators. Al-
though DIFUSCO can handle problems with up to 10,000
nodes, it is less suitable for time-sensitive scenarios. Point-
erformer (Jin et al. 2023) incorporates a reversible resid-
ual network in the encoder and a multi-pointer network in
the decoder, allowing it to solve problems with up to 1000
nodes. Search-based approaches start with a feasible so-
lution and iteratively apply predefined rules to improve it.
NeuRewriter (Chen and Tian 2019) iteratively rewrites local
components through a region-picking and rule-picking pro-
cess, with the model trained using Advantage Actor-Critic,
and the reduced cost per iteration serves as the reward. Neu-
roLKH (Xin et al. 2021) enhances the traditional LKH3
solver by employing a sparse graph network trained through
supervised learning to simultaneously generate edge scores
and node penalties, which guide the improvement process.
DeepACO (Ye et al. 2024a) integrates neural enhancements
into Ant Colony Optimization (ACO) algorithms, further
Machine learning-based algorithms perform well on TSP
instances with up to 1,000 nodes, but struggle with larger
instances due to the exponential increase in memory re-
quirements and computation time as the number of nodes
grows. This leads to memory and time constraints during
training, making it difficult to converge to near-optimal solu-
tions. To address this challenge in solving large-scale prob-
lems with thousands or more nodes, the divide-and-conquer
strategy is often employed. It is always combined with tradi-
tional or learning-based algorithms to generate high-quality
solutions in a relatively short time. GCN-MCTS (Fu, Qiu,
and Zha 2021) applies graph sampling to construct fixed-
size sub-problems, solved by graph convolutional networks,
with heatmaps guiding Monte-Carlo Tree Search (MCTS).
H-TSP (Pan et al. 2023) hierarchically builds TSP solu-
tions using a two-level policy: the upper-level selects sub-
problems, while the lower-level generates and merges open-
loop routes. ExtNCO (Chen et al. 2023) uses LocKMeans
with o(n) complexity to divide nodes into sub-problems,
solving them with neural combinatorial optimization and
merging solutions via a minimum spanning tree. GLOP
(Ye et al. 2024b) learns global partition heatmaps to de-
compose large-scale problems and introduces a scalable
real-time solver for small Shortest Hamiltonian Path prob-
lems. UDC (Zheng et al. 2024) proposes a Divide-Conquer-
Reunion framework using efficient Graph Neural Networks
for division and fixed-length solvers for sub-problems. Soft-
Dist (Xia et al. 2024) demonstrates that a simple base-
line method outperforms complex machine learning ap-
proaches in heatmap generation, and the heatmap-guided
MCTS paradigm is inferior to the LKH3 heuristic despite

=== PAGE 3 ===
The Proposed DualOpt Algorithm
The proposed DualOpt algorithm is based on and extends the
basic divide-and-conquer method by incorporating a grid-
based procedure and a path-based procedure to improve effi-
ciency. Each procedure operates on two levels: the first level
is responsible for generating sub-problems, while the second
level focuses on solving these sub-problems.
Algorithm 1: The Proposed DualOpt Algorithm for
Input: TSP instance V = {v1, v2, · · · , vN}
Output: Solution route τ
1 PartialRoutesSet Υ ←∅;
2 NodesSet ℵ←V ;
Grids ←Partition(Υ, ℵ) ;
Routes ←SolveGridsParallel(Υ, ℵ) ;
Υ′, ℵ′ ←EdgeBreaking(Routes) ;
9 until predefined iterations reached;
10 τ ←SolveReducedProb(Υ, ℵ) ;
τ ′ ←MergeSubPath(SubPath′) ;
16 until predefined iterations reached;
The whole procedure of DualOpt is summarized in Algo-
rithm 1. It starts by partitioning the TSP instance into smaller
grids, which reduces the problem size and allows for parallel
solving. In each iteration, the partial routes and nodes within
each grid are solved in parallel to generate a solution for
that portion of the TSP. Next, an edge-breaking procedure is
applied to divide each route into smaller partial routes and
nodes. The grids are then merged into larger ones using a
grid merging procedure. This grid-based iteration continues
until only one grid remains, forming a reduced problem that
consists of a number of partial routes and nodes. From this
reduced problem, a high-quality initial solution of is con-
structed. To further refine the solution, it is divided into sub-
paths, which are optimized in batches and then merged. This
iterative refinement, performed with varying partition sizes,
progressively improves the solution quality.
A Grid-based Divide-and-Conquer Procedure
To decompose the large-scale TSP for efficient solving with-
out significantly downgrading solution quality, we employ
an iterative grid decomposition strategy, denoted as the Grid-
based Divide-and-Conquer Procedure, as depicted in Algo-
rithm 2. Initially, the node set ℵcontains all the nodes of
the TSP instance, while the partial route set Υ is initialized
as empty. In each iteration, the 2D space is discretized into
an evenly spaced grid of size K = 2Niter−iter × 2Niter−iter
grids. The node set ℵand partial route set Υ are then divided
into K subsets {(Υ1, ℵ1), . . . , (ΥK, ℵK)} based on their
positions within the grid. Each of these subsets is solved
in parallel using the well-known TSP solver LKH3 (Hels-
gaun 2017), resulting in K small routes {R1, . . . , RK}. If
the current iteration (iter) is not the last one, the algorithm
proceeds by applying a proposed edge-breaking strategy in
parallel, which breaks a subset of the edges of the routes and
updates Υ and ℵwith new sets of partial routes and nodes
K)}. As the iterations progress, K
decreases and the grid size increases correspondingly until
only one grid remains. At this final stage, a reduced problem
consisting of partial routes and nodes is formed, from which
an initial high-quality TSP solution τ is obtained.
Algorithm 2: Grid-based Divide-and-Conquer
Input: TSP instance V = {v1, v2, ..., vN}, number of
Output: Solution route τ
2 NodesSet ℵ←V ;
3 PartialRoutesSet Υ ←∅;
4 while iter ≤Niter do
K ←2Niter−iter × 2Niter−iter; /*Calculate the
{(Υ1, ℵ1), . . . , (ΥK, ℵK)} ←Partition(Υ, ℵ, K);
/*Partition nodes and partial routes into grids*/
SolveGridsParallel({(Υ1, ℵ1), . . . , (ΥK, ℵK)});
/*Solve the TSP for each grid in parallel*/
if iter ̸= Niter then
BreakEdgesParallel({R1, . . . , RK}; /*Break
edges into partial routes and nodes in parallel*/
Υ is updated by {Υ′
ℵis updated by {ℵ′
τ ←SolveReducedProb(Υ, ℵ) ; /*Solve the
reduced problem to get a complete route*/
iter ←iter + 1 ;
Figure 1 illustrates this procedure with Niter = 3. In
the first iteration, K is 16, partitioning the 2D space into
16 evenly spaced grids. The LKH3 generates 16 localized
routes per grid, which are then decomposed into partial
routes and separate nodes. In the second iteration, K is re-
duced to 4, resulting in 4 larger grids where the LKH3 pro-
cesses partial routes with fixed nodes. In the final iteration,
K is reduced to 1, merging the grids into a single one. As a
result, the number of nodes decreases while the number of
partial routes increases. This reduction in problem scale en-
ables the LKH3 solver to efficiently find a TSP solution with
The LKH3 Solver The LKH3 solver, a state-of-the-art
heuristic for the TSP, is built upon the foundational Lin-
Kernighan heuristic, incorporating several advanced compo-

=== PAGE 4 ===
Figure 1: An illustration of the Grid-based Divide-and-
Conquer Procedure with Niter = 3.
nents. Among these, the use of a 1-tree structure is particu-
larly notable, as it provides a lower bound that guides the
search process effectively. The algorithm dynamically em-
ploys K-opt neighborhood operators, where multiple edges
are iteratively removed and reconnected to explore potential
routes within the solution space. The efficiency of LKH3
is further enhanced by using candidate sets, which strategi-
cally limits the number of neighborhood operators, thereby
The number of nodes within each grid, typically rang-
ing from a few hundreds to approximately one thousand,
is determined by both the instance scale and the number of
grids K. The input to the solver includes not only the co-
ordinates of nodes but also the fixed partial routes. LKH3
excels in handling node scales within this range, deliver-
ing high-quality solutions with remarkable speed, particu-
larly for routing problems involving fixed edges. Therefore,
LKH3 was selected as the subsolver for this study.
Edge-breaking Strategy Recall that multiple routes are
generated, one for each grid within the 2D space. When
merging and optimizing these routes, it is essential to
reschedule the surrounding nodes of each grid in conjunc-
tion with the nodes of adjacent grids, while excluding the in-
ternal nodes from this rescheduling process. To achieve this,
we propose an edge-breaking strategy that effectively re-
duces the problem’s scale. Specifically, for each grid, we de-
fine an internal grid that maintains a fixed spacing from the
outer grid. This spacing is calculated as spacing = xmax−xmin
where xmax and xmin denote the maximum and minimum
x-coordinates of the grid, respectively. We then remove all
edges that lie outside the internal grid, as well as those cross-
ing into it. As a result, the nodes and edges within the inter-
nal grid form several partial routes that each may consist of
more than two connected nodes, along with isolated nodes.
A Path-based Divide-and-Optimize Procedure
Based on the solution derived from the grid-based divide-
and-conquer procedure, further optimization is achieved
through the path-based divide-and-optimize procedure, as
detailed in Algorithm 3. Following previous studies (Kim,
Park et al. 2021; Ye et al. 2024b; Zheng et al. 2024), this it-
erative algorithm aims to refine an initial solution τ by parti-
tioning it into smaller sub-paths, optimizing these sub-paths
individually, and then merging them to generate an improved
The procedure begins by iterating over a specified
set of sub-path lengths len1, . . . , lenm and iterations
iter1, . . . , iterm. For each sub-path length len, the initial
solution τ is divided into sub-paths of the designated length.
If the length of the last sub-path is shorter than the desig-
nated length, it remains unchanged. Each sub-path can be
considered as an open-loop TSP with two fixed endpoints.
These sub-paths undergo a distribution normalization of ver-
tex coordinates to maintain consistency with the original
TSP instance, resulting in normalized sub-paths denoted as
′. Following normalization, a neural solver is
employed in batch mode to optimize the normalized sub-
paths, and sub-paths are updated by the policy when they
are better than the current ones, producing a set of sub-
paths SubPathSet∗. These sub-paths are then merged to
form an improved solution τ ∗by connecting their fixed end-
points in their original order. To ensure continuous refine-
ment and overlap during the iterations, the starting point κ
for sub-path division is incremented by max(1, len
iterative refinement process is repeated for each combination
of sub-path length and iteration count, progressively refining
the manageable sub-paths of the initial solution τ to yield a
highly optimized solution τ ∗.
Algorithm 3: Path-based Divide-and-Optimize
Input: Solution τ = {τ1, τ2, ..., τN}, a set of sub-path
lengths{len1, . . . , lenm}, and a set of iterations
{iter1, . . . , iterm}
Output: Optimized Solution τ ∗
1 for len ←len1 to lenm do
for iter ←iter1 to iterm do
SubPathSet ←{τκ:κ+len, τκ+len:κ+2len, . . .};
κ ←κ + max(1, len
Neural Solver The underlying solver of the path-based
divide-and-optimize procedure is an attention-based neural
network, which can efficiently solve the obtained sub-paths
The neural network uses an encoder-decoder architecture.
The encoder employs self-attention layers to embed the in-
put node sequence, while the decoder generates the node se-
quence auto-regressively. Each sub-path π can be regarded
as an open-loop TSP with specified start and end nodes. We

=== PAGE 5 ===
employ a modified context embedding inspired by (Kim,
Park et al. 2021), defined as h(L)
Here, h denotes a high-dimensional embedding vector from
the encoder, and L represents the number of multi-head at-
(L) is the mean of the final node embed-
πpre is the embedding of the previously selected
πdes is embedding of the end node of the sub-
path. Moreover, following insights from previous studies
(Kim, Park et al. 2021; Cheng et al. 2023; Ye et al. 2024b),
we leverage the symmetry of sub-paths. Specifically, revers-
ing the traversal direction of a sub-path (moving backward
versus forward) yields an equivalent sequence, which helps
improve the network’s robustness and efficiency.
The network employs a single-step constructive policy
aimed at optimizing the solution by generating sequences in
both forward and backward directions. The policy is defined
as follows, where s represents a sub-path with a start node
π1 and an end node πn. The policy pθ(πf, πb|s) is parame-
terized by θ and specifies a stochastic policy for constructing
the forward solution πf and the backward solution πb:
pθ(πf, πb|s) = pθ(πf|s)pθ(πb|s)
pθ(π1+t|s, π1:t, πn) ×
The model is trained using REINFORCE with a shared
baseline. The objective is to minimize the expected length of
the solutions to the sub-problems. To achieve this, the loss
function is defined as the expected length of these solutions.
The policy gradient is then computed as follows:
▽L(θ|s) =Epθ(πf |s)[R(πf) −b(s)]▽log pθ(πf|s)
+ Epθ(πb|s)[R(πb) −b(s)]▽log pθ(πb|s).
The shared baseline b(s) is employed to reduce variance
and enhance training stability. This baseline is computed by
averaging the path lengths obtained from two greedy roll-
outs. Note that during model training, both forward and
backward solutions are utilized. However, during inference,
only the superior trajectory between the two solutions is se-
lected to ensure the best possible outcome.
Node Coordinate Normalization To improve the robust-
ness of the model with respect to the sub-paths, we nor-
malize the node coordinates to be uniformly distributed
within the range [0, 1] (Fu, Qiu, and Zha 2021). We de-
fine xmax = maxi∈G xi, xmin = mini∈G xi, ymax =
maxi∈G yi, ymin = mini∈G yi as the maximum and min-
imum values of the horizontal and vertical coordinates of all
N nodes in the TSP instance. For each node in the sub-path,
we convert its coordinate (xi, yi) to (x
i) as shown in Eq.
(3), ensuring that all coordinates fall within the range [0, 1].
max(xmax −xmin, ymax −ymin),
max(xmax −xmin, ymax −ymin).
To evaluate the performance of our proposed DualOpt, we
conducted extensive experiments on the large-scale TSP in-
stances, with up to 100,000 nodes. We compared the perfor-
mance of DualOpt with that of state-of-the-art algorithms
from the literature. All experiments, including rerunning
the baseline algorithms, were executed on a machine with
an RTX 3080(10GB) GPU and a 12-core Intel(R) Xeon(R)
Our evaluation focused on two groups of the large-
scale instances: randomly generated instances TSP random
and the well-known real-world benchmark TSPLIB. The
TSP random represents random Euclidean instances, with
node coordinates uniformly sampled from a unit square
[0, 1]2. This group includes seven datasets, each correspond-
ing to a different number of nodes, denoted as TSPN, i.e.,
TSP1K (1,000 nodes), TSP2K, TSP5K, TSP10K, TSP20K,
TSP50K, and TSP100K (100,000 nodes). For a fair com-
parison, we used the same test instances provided by Fu et
al. (Fu, Qiu, and Zha 2021) and Pan et al. (Pan et al. 2023).
Each dataset contains 16 instances, except TSP1K, which in-
cludes 128 instances, and TSP100K, which contains one in-
stance. The TSPLIB is a well-known real-world benchmark
(Reinelt 1991) that consists of 100 instances with diverse
node distributions derived from practical applications, with
sizes ranging from 14 to 85,900 nodes. For our experiments,
we select the ten largest TSPLIB instances, each containing
more than 5,000 nodes.
We compare DualOpt against ten leading TSP
algorithms in the literature. Traditional Algorithms: 1)
Concorde (Cook et al. 2011): One of the best exact solvers.
2) LKH3 (Helsgaun 2017): One of the highly optimized
heuristic solvers. Machine Learning Based Algorithms:
1) POMO (Kwon et al. 2020): Feature an end-to-end model
based on Attention Model, comparable to LKH3 for small-
scale TSP instances. 2) DIMES (Qiu, Sun, and Yang 2022):
Introduce a compact continuous space for parameterizing
the underlying distribution of candidate solutions for solv-
ing large-scale TSP with up to 10K nodes. 3) DIFUSO (Sun
and Yang 2024): Leverage a graph-based denoising diffu-
sion model to solve large-scale TSP with up to 10K nodes.
4) SIL (Luo et al. 2024): Develop an efficient self-improved
mechanism that enables direct model training on large-scale
problem instances without labeled data, handling TSP in-
stances with up to 100K nodes. Divide-and-Conquer Algo-
rithms: 1) GCN+MCTS (Fu, Qiu, and Zha 2021): Combine
a GCN model trained with supervised learning and MCTS
to solve large-scale TSP involving up to 10K nodes with a
long searching time. 2) SoftDist (Xia et al. 2024): Critically
evaluate machine learning guided heatmap generation, the
heatmap-guided MCTS paradigm for large-scale TSP. 3) H-
TSP (Pan et al. 2023): Hierarchically construct a solution
of a TSP instance with up to 10K nodes based on two-level
policies. 4) GLOP (Ye et al. 2024b): Decompose large rout-
ing problems into Shortest Hamiltonian Path Problems, fur-
ther improved by local policy. It is the first neural solver to
effectively scale to TSP with up to 100K nodes.

=== PAGE 6 ===
conquer procedure, we set the value of Niter for differ-
ent TSP problem scales, as shown in Table 1. The LKH3
solver is used with its default parameters as specified in the
literature (Helsgaun 2017) both in DualOpt and baseline.
LKH3 baseline runs instance-by-instance. In the grid-based
divide-and-conquer stage, LKH3 sub-solver just run paral-
lel for grids in a single instance. For the path-based divide-
and-optimize procedure, we train different neural solvers
with graph size len = {50, 20, 10}, with node coordinates
randomly generated from a uniform distribution within a
unit square. During the training process, we use the same
hyper-parameter settings as those used by Kool et al (Kool,
van Hoof, and Welling 2019). And during test time, we set
iter = {25, 10, 5}. Our code is publicly available.1
Problem Scale of TSP
5, 000 ≤N < 20, 000
20, 000 ≤N < 100, 000
Table 1: Parameter setting of Niter.
Table 2 presents a comparison of
10 leading algorithms and our DualOpt algorithm on ran-
domly distributed datasets TSP random. The “Obj.” col-
umn shows the average objective lengths of the routes
obtained by each algorithm for each instance, while the
“Gap” column measures the percentage difference between
the average route lengths attained by each algorithm and
the LKH3, considered as the ground truth, i.e., Gap =
Obj. of Algo. - Obj of LKH3
× 100%. The “Time” column indicates
the average time required to solve each instance. The † fol-
lowing the algorithm indicates that the results of this algo-
rithm are drawn from the literature directly and “-” means
the results are not provided in the literature. The “OOM”
stands for out of CUDA memory with our platform.
From Table 2, we can make the following comments
about the TSP random instances. First, the heuristic solver
LKH3 provides the highest quality solutions for all instances
except TSP1K and TSP2K, though it requires long time
searching. DualOpt matches or improves upon LKH3’s re-
sults for all instances except TSP5K, and achieves an im-
proved result with an improvement gap up to 1.40% for the
largest instance TSP100K, with a remarkable 104x speed-
up. Second, DualOpt clearly outperforms machine learning
based algorithms in both solution quality and running time.
POMO underperforms across all instances, primarily be-
cause it cannot be trained directly on large-scale instances,
and models trained on small-scale instances fail to gener-
alize effectively to large-scale instances. Compared to the
current state-of-the-art SIL, our DualOpt surpasses SIL in
all instances except for a tie on TSP1K. Third, DualOpt con-
sistently outperforms all four divide-and-conquer algorithms
in terms of the best objective result, achieving better results
than GLOP for all instances. These observations highlight
the superiority of DualOpt in both solution quality and com-
To demonstrate the solver’s generalization capabilities,
we then directly applied the trained neural solver to the
real-world dataset TSPLIB with varied distributions. Ta-
ble 3 presents the results for the 10 largest instances from
TSPLIB. Despite the different node distributions in TSPLIB
compared to those in TSP random, DualOpt demonstrates
impressive generalization capabilities. It achieves highly
competitive results compared to three leading large-scale
TSP algorithms from the literature. This performance high-
lights DualOpt’s effectiveness in handling various types of
TSP instances and further underscores its versatility in real-
Our DualOpt integrates two im-
portant divide-and-conquer procedures to achieve superior
performance. To evaluate the impact of each procedure,
we conducted an ablation study with two distinct vari-
ants of DualOpt: DualOptw/oP ath and DualOptw/oGrid.
DualOptw/oP ath employs only the grid-based divide-and-
conquer procedure, while DualOptw/oGrid generates the ini-
tial solution using a simple yet effective approach called
random insertion, which is then improved using the path-
based divide-and-optimize procedure. The results of this ab-
lation study are summarized in Table 4. The comparative re-
sults clearly demonstrate the significance of both procedures
within DualOpt. Specifically, the original DualOpt consis-
tently outperforms the variants, underscoring the importance
of combining both the grid-based and path-based procedures
for achieving superior performance.
In this paper, we introduced a novel dual divide-and-
optimize algorithm DualOpt to solve large-scale traveling
salesman problem, which integrates two complementary
strategies: a grid-based divide-and-conquer procedure and a
path-based divide-and-optimize procedure. Through exten-
sive experiments on randomly generated instances and real-
world datasets, DualOpt consistently achieves highly com-
petitive results with state-of-the-art TSP algorithms in terms
of both solution quality and computational efficiency. More-
over, DualOpt is able to generalize across different TSP
distributions, making it a versatile solver for tackling di-
verse real-world TSP applications. The success of DualOpt
paves the way for future research into more sophisticated
divide-and-conquer strategies and their application to differ-
ent types of other combinatorial optimization problems.
This work is supported by National Natural Science Foun-
Accorsi, L.; and Vigo, D. 2021. A fast and scalable heuris-
tic for the solution of large-scale capacitated vehicle routing
problems. Transportation Science, 55(4): 832–856.

=== PAGE 7 ===
Table 2: Comparative results with 10 leading algorithms on large-scale TSP random with up to 100K nodes.
Table 3: Comparative results on 10 largest instances of TSPLIB.
Table 4: An ablation study of DualOpt and its two variants on TSP random
Applegate, D. L.; Bixby, R. E.; Chv´atal, V.; Cook, W.; Es-
pinoza, D. G.; Goycoolea, M.; and Helsgaun, K. 2009. Cer-
tification of an optimal TSP tour through 85,900 cities. Op-
erations Research Letters, 37(1): 11–15.
Chen, X.; Li, Y.; Yang, Y.; Zhang, L.; Li, S.; and Pan, G.
Extnco: A Fine-Grained Divide-and-Conquer Ap-

