=== EXPERIMENTS START AT PAGE 6 ===
--- PAGE 6 ---
conquer procedure, we set the value of Niter for differ-
ent TSP problem scales, as shown in Table 1. The LKH3
solver is used with its default parameters as specified in the
literature (Helsgaun 2017) both in DualOpt and baseline.
LKH3 baseline runs instance-by-instance. In the grid-based
divide-and-conquer stage, LKH3 sub-solver just run paral-
lel for grids in a single instance. For the path-based divide-
and-optimize procedure, we train different neural solvers
with graph size len = {50, 20, 10}, with node coordinates
randomly generated from a uniform distribution within a
unit square. During the training process, we use the same
hyper-parameter settings as those used by Kool et al (Kool,
van Hoof, and Welling 2019). And during test time, we set
iter = {25, 10, 5}. Our code is publicly available.1
Problem Scale of TSP
5, 000 ≤N < 20, 000
20, 000 ≤N < 100, 000
Table 1: Parameter setting of Niter.
Table 2 presents a comparison of
10 leading algorithms and our DualOpt algorithm on ran-
domly distributed datasets TSP random. The “Obj.” col-
umn shows the average objective lengths of the routes
obtained by each algorithm for each instance, while the
“Gap” column measures the percentage difference between
the average route lengths attained by each algorithm and
the LKH3, considered as the ground truth, i.e., Gap =
Obj. of Algo. - Obj of LKH3
× 100%. The “Time” column indicates
the average time required to solve each instance. The † fol-
lowing the algorithm indicates that the results of this algo-
rithm are drawn from the literature directly and “-” means
the results are not provided in the literature. The “OOM”
stands for out of CUDA memory with our platform.
From Table 2, we can make the following comments
about the TSP random instances. First, the heuristic solver
LKH3 provides the highest quality solutions for all instances
except TSP1K and TSP2K, though it requires long time
searching. DualOpt matches or improves upon LKH3’s re-
sults for all instances except TSP5K, and achieves an im-
proved result with an improvement gap up to 1.40% for the
largest instance TSP100K, with a remarkable 104x speed-
up. Second, DualOpt clearly outperforms machine learning
based algorithms in both solution quality and running time.
POMO underperforms across all instances, primarily be-
cause it cannot be trained directly on large-scale instances,
and models trained on small-scale instances fail to gener-
alize effectively to large-scale instances. Compared to the
current state-of-the-art SIL, our DualOpt surpasses SIL in
all instances except for a tie on TSP1K. Third, DualOpt con-
sistently outperforms all four divide-and-conquer algorithms
in terms of the best objective result, achieving better results
than GLOP for all instances. These observations highlight
the superiority of DualOpt in both solution quality and com-
To demonstrate the solver’s generalization capabilities,
we then directly applied the trained neural solver to the
real-world dataset TSPLIB with varied distributions. Ta-
ble 3 presents the results for the 10 largest instances from
TSPLIB. Despite the different node distributions in TSPLIB
compared to those in TSP random, DualOpt demonstrates
impressive generalization capabilities. It achieves highly
competitive results compared to three leading large-scale
TSP algorithms from the literature. This performance high-
lights DualOpt’s effectiveness in handling various types of
TSP instances and further underscores its versatility in real-
Our DualOpt integrates two im-
portant divide-and-conquer procedures to achieve superior
performance. To evaluate the impact of each procedure,
we conducted an ablation study with two distinct vari-
ants of DualOpt: DualOptw/oP ath and DualOptw/oGrid.
DualOptw/oP ath employs only the grid-based divide-and-
conquer procedure, while DualOptw/oGrid generates the ini-
tial solution using a simple yet effective approach called
random insertion, which is then improved using the path-
based divide-and-optimize procedure. The results of this ab-
lation study are summarized in Table 4. The comparative re-
sults clearly demonstrate the significance of both procedures
within DualOpt. Specifically, the original DualOpt consis-
tently outperforms the variants, underscoring the importance
of combining both the grid-based and path-based procedures
for achieving superior performance.
In this paper, we introduced a novel dual divide-and-
optimize algorithm DualOpt to solve large-scale traveling
salesman problem, which integrates two complementary
strategies: a grid-based divide-and-conquer procedure and a
path-based divide-and-optimize procedure. Through exten-
sive experiments on randomly generated instances and real-
world datasets, DualOpt consistently achieves highly com-
petitive results with state-of-the-art TSP algorithms in terms
of both solution quality and computational efficiency. More-
over, DualOpt is able to generalize across different TSP
distributions, making it a versatile solver for tackling di-
verse real-world TSP applications. The success of DualOpt
paves the way for future research into more sophisticated
divide-and-conquer strategies and their application to differ-
ent types of other combinatorial optimization problems.
This work is supported by National Natural Science Foun-
Accorsi, L.; and Vigo, D. 2021. A fast and scalable heuris-
tic for the solution of large-scale capacitated vehicle routing
problems. Transportation Science, 55(4): 832–856.

--- PAGE 7 ---
Table 2: Comparative results with 10 leading algorithms on large-scale TSP random with up to 100K nodes.
Table 3: Comparative results on 10 largest instances of TSPLIB.
Table 4: An ablation study of DualOpt and its two variants on TSP random
Applegate, D. L.; Bixby, R. E.; Chv´atal, V.; Cook, W.; Es-
pinoza, D. G.; Goycoolea, M.; and Helsgaun, K. 2009. Cer-
tification of an optimal TSP tour through 85,900 cities. Op-
erations Research Letters, 37(1): 11–15.
Chen, X.; Li, Y.; Yang, Y.; Zhang, L.; Li, S.; and Pan, G.
Extnco: A Fine-Grained Divide-and-Conquer Ap-

--- PAGE 8 ---
proach for Extending Nco to Solve Large-Scale Traveling
Salesman Problem. Available at SSRN 4679437.
Chen, X.; and Tian, Y. 2019.
Learning to perform local
rewriting for combinatorial optimization. Advances in neu-
ral information processing systems, 32.
Cheng, H.; Zheng, H.; Cong, Y.; Jiang, W.; and Pu, S. 2023.
Select and optimize: Learning to solve large-scale tsp in-
In International Conference on Artificial Intelli-
gence and Statistics, 1219–1231. PMLR.
Cook, W. J.; Applegate, D. L.; Bixby, R. E.; and Chvatal,
V. 2011. The traveling salesman problem: a computational
study. Princeton university press.
Fu, Z.-H.; Qiu, K.-B.; and Zha, H. 2021. Generalize a small
pre-trained model to arbitrarily large tsp instances. In Pro-
ceedings of the AAAI conference on artificial intelligence,
Gutin, G.; and Punnen, A. P. 2006. The traveling salesman
problem and its variations, volume 12. Springer Science &
Hacizade, U.; and Kaya, I. 2018.
Salesman Problem Solution and its Application to Transport
Routes Optimization. IFAC-PapersOnLine 51 (30): 620–
An extension of the Lin-Kernighan-
Helsgaun TSP solver for constrained traveling salesman and
vehicle routing problems. Roskilde: Roskilde University, 12.
Hou, Q.; Yang, J.; Su, Y.; Wang, X.; and Deng, Y. 2023.
Generalize learned heuristics to solve large-scale vehicle
routing problems in real-time. In The Eleventh International
Conference on Learning Representations.
Jin, Y.; Ding, Y.; Pan, X.; He, K.; Zhao, L.; Qin, T.; Song,
L.; and Bian, J. 2023. Pointerformer: Deep reinforced multi-
pointer transformer for the traveling salesman problem. In
Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelli-
gence, volume 37, 8132–8140.
Joshi, C. K.; Cappart, Q.; Rousseau, L.-M.; and Laurent, T.
2022. Learning the travelling salesperson problem requires
rethinking generalization. Constraints, 27(1-2): 70–98.
Kim, M.; Park, J.; et al. 2021. Learning collaborative poli-
cies to solve NP-hard routing problems. Advances in Neural
Information Processing Systems, 34: 10418–10430.
Kool, W.; van Hoof, H.; and Welling, M. 2019. Attention,
Learn to Solve Routing Problems! In International Confer-
ence on Learning Representations.
Kwon, Y.-D.; Choo, J.; Kim, B.; Yoon, I.; Gwon, Y.; and
Min, S. 2020. Pomo: Policy optimization with multiple op-
tima for reinforcement learning. Advances in Neural Infor-
mation Processing Systems, 33: 21188–21198.
Luo, F.; Lin, X.; Wang, Z.; Xialiang, T.; Yuan, M.;
and Zhang, Q. 2024.
Self-Improved Learning for Scal-
able Neural Combinatorial Optimization.
Madani, A.; Batta, R.; and Karwan, M. 2021. The balancing
traveling salesman problem: application to warehouse order
picking. Top, 29: 442–469.
Matai, R.; Singh, S. P.; and Mittal, M. L. 2010. Traveling
salesman problem: an overview of applications, formula-
tions, and solution approaches. Traveling salesman problem,
theory and applications, 1(1): 1–25.
Pan, X.; Jin, Y.; Ding, Y.; Feng, M.; Zhao, L.; Song, L.; and
Bian, J. 2023. H-tsp: Hierarchically solving the large-scale
In Proceedings of the AAAI
Conference on Artificial Intelligence, volume 37, 9345–
Qiu, R.; Sun, Z.; and Yang, Y. 2022. Dimes: A differen-
tiable meta solver for combinatorial optimization problems.
Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, 35:
Reinelt, G. 1991. TSPLIB—A traveling salesman problem
library. ORSA journal on computing, 3(4): 376–384.
Sun, Z.; and Yang, Y. 2024. Difusco: Graph-based diffusion
solvers for combinatorial optimization. Advances in Neural
Information Processing Systems, 36.
Toth, P.; and Vigo, D. 2002. The vehicle routing problem.
Vaswani, A.; Shazeer, N.; Parmar, N.; Uszkoreit, J.; Jones,
L.; Gomez, A. N.; Kaiser, Ł.; and Polosukhin, I. 2017. At-
tention is all you need. Advances in neural information pro-
Wiering, M. A.; and Van Otterlo, M. 2012. Reinforcement
Adaptation, learning, and optimization, 12(3):
Xia, Y.; Yang, X.; Liu, Z.; Liu, Z.; Song, L.; and Bian, J.
Position: Rethinking Post-Hoc Search-Based Neu-
ral Approaches for Solving Large-Scale Traveling Salesman
Problems. In Proceedings of the 41st International Confer-
ence on Machine Learning, 54178–54190.
Xin, L.; Song, W.; Cao, Z.; and Zhang, J. 2021.
rolkh: Combining deep learning model with lin-kernighan-
helsgaun heuristic for solving the traveling salesman prob-
lem. Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems,
Ye, H.; Wang, J.; Cao, Z.; Liang, H.; and Li, Y. 2024a. Deep-
ACO: Neural-enhanced Ant Systems for Combinatorial Op-
timization. Advances in Neural Information Processing Sys-
Ye, H.; Wang, J.; Liang, H.; Cao, Z.; Li, Y.; and Li, F. 2024b.
Glop: Learning global partition and local construction for
solving large-scale routing problems in real-time. In Pro-
ceedings of the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence,
Zheng, Z.; Zhou, C.; Xialiang, T.; Yuan, M.; and Wang, Z.
2024. UDC: A Unified Neural Divide-and-Conquer Frame-
work for Large-Scale Combinatorial Optimization Prob-
lems. In The Thirty-eighth Annual Conference on Neural

